Guide to the Gordon Alexander Craig Papers SC0467
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Gordon Alexander Craig papers
1934-2006
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Craig, Gordon Alexander
SC0467
20.25 Linear Feet
Scope and Content
These papers largely reflect Gordon A. Craig's career as a historian and professor at Stanford University from 1961 through 1979. In addition, there are some materials pertaining to his student days at Princeton University and Oxford, to his early teaching career at Yale and Princeton, and to his teaching and administrative duties as a professor at the Free University of Berlin. The collection, donated by Gordon A. Craig in six accessions, includes more than 45 boxes of correspondence, lectures, speeches, articles, publications, class materials, student papers, research notes, notebooks, and newspaper clippings. The collection also includes microfilmed copies of his personal diaries, 1935-1992, and occasional verse, 1934-1986.
Biography
Born in Glasgow, Scotland in 1913, Gordon Craig immigrated to the United States from Canada with his parents at the age of 12. He was educated at Princeton University where, as Valedictorian, he received his A.B. in 1936, followed by an M.A. in 1939 and a Ph.D. in 1941. As a Rhodes Scholar in 1938, he received a B.Litt. from Oxford University. He began his teaching career at Yale in 1939, but returned to the Department of History at Princeton in 1941.
During World War II, Dr. Craig worked in Washington as a research associate for the Office of Strategic Services and as a divisional assistant for the Special Division of the Department of State. He earned a commission in the U.S. Marine Corps and after a tour of duty in the Central Pacific, Dr. Craig resumed his teaching at Princeton University in 1946. In 1950, Dr. Craig received full professorship at Princeton at the age of 37. He was a frequent lecturer at the National War College and served as Chairman of the Editorial Board of the Princeton University Marine Corps History Project, which in 1951 published The U.S. Marines and Amphibious War, a scientific study of the Marines' working principles of warfare.
Gordon Craig moved to Stanford University in 1961, and became the first recipient of the J. E. Wallace Sterling Endowed Professorship in the Humanities in 1969. The Sterling Professorship was created in 1968 by the Stanford Board of Trustees in honor of Dr. Sterling, who resigned after 19 years as Stanford's president to become lifetime chancellor of the University.
Dr. Craig was appointed an honorary professor by the Berlin Senate in 1962 and served as member of the faculty of the Free University of Berlin during the remainder of his career at Stanford. In 1970, Dr. Craig received an honorary Litt.D. from Princeton University and in 1972 received an honorary degree from Wake Forest University.
As Chairman of the Department of History at Stanford from 1972 to 1975 and again in 1979, and Chairman of the Faculty Senate for the 1974-75 academic year, Dr. Craig worked to strengthen the Department of History as well as the University's undergraduate and graduate teaching programs. In addition he helped to redesign Stanford University's overseas programs as head of the Committee on Foreign Study Programs in 1974. He was the recipient of the Lloyd W. Dinkelspiel Award for Outstanding Service to Undergraduate Education in 1973.
Among his many activities and honors, Craig serving as a visiting professor at Columbia University, a fellow in the Center of Advanced Study of Behavioral Sciences in Stanford, California, a member of the Civilian Faculty Selection Advisory Committee of the National War College, a member of the Social Science Advisory Board of the United States Arms Control and Disarmament Agency, President of the Pacific Coast Branch of the American Historical Association, and Second and First Vice President of the Comite International des Sciences Historiques. He was a frequent Phi Beta Kappa lecturer and served on the Senate of the United Chapters of Phi Beta Kappa from 1979 through 1985. He was elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences as well as the American Philosophical Association in 1962, and served as President of the American Historical Association in 1982.
An international authority on European diplomatic and military history and modern European and German history, Craig is the author of numerous scholarly publications on these and other subjects. His publications include: The Diplomats, 1919-1939; Makers of Modern Strategy; Europe Since 1815, a widely-used textbook; From Bismarck to Adenauer: Aspects of German Statecraft; The Politics of the Prussian Army, 1640-1945, for which he received the H. B. Adams Prize of the American Historical Association in 1955; The Battle of Koniggraetz: Prussia's victory over Austria, 1866; On the Diplomatic Revolution of Our Time; War Politics and Diplomacy: Selected Essays; Germany, 1866-1945, for which he received the Historian's Peace Prize of the City of Munster, Germany in 1981; Uber die Deutschen, for which he received an award for the best book about Germany from abroad from the Friedrich-Ebert-Stiftung of Bonn in 1988; The Triumph of Liberalism, for which he received Switzerland's major literary honor, "The Gift of Honor," in 1988; and Knowledge and Power: Historical Essays and Essays About History. Professor Craig served on the editorial board of several journals and was a frequent contributor to the New York Review of Books, and the New York Times Review of Books. Consistently voted one of the best lecturers at both Princeton and Stanford, Professor Craig wrote many articles on teaching as well. Dr. Craig became an emeritus professor in 1979.
Provenance
Gift of Gordon A. Craig, 1993-1996
Access Restrictions
The materials are open for research use.
Germany -- History.; Diaries.; Europe -- History.; lectures; Craig, Gordon Alexander; Stanford University. Department of History -- General subdivision--Faculty.
- Correspondence, 1941-1991; Series 1
  - Chronological
    - January - May, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - June - August, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - September, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - October, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - November, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - December, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - January, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - January, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - February, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - March, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - April - May 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - June - July, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - August - September, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - October, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - November - December, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - January, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - February - March, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - April, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - May - June, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - July - August, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - September, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - October, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - November, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - December, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - January, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - February, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - March, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - April, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - May, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - June, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - July, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - August, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - January - October, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - November - December, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - January - February, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - March - April, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - May - June, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - July - August, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - September - November, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Subject Related
    - The Atlantic Council (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Berlin, Free University of, 1959-1962 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Berlin, Free University of, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Berlin, Free University of, 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Berlin Historical Commission (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Cranks, Crackpots, and Beefs, 1947-1950 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Cranks, Crackpots, and Beefs, 1951-1953 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Cranks, Crackpots, and Beefs, 1954-1958 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Scope and Contents note
      Folders 1-3 "Cranks, Crackpots, and Beefs," include responses to Craig's reviews of John Flynn's The Lattimore Story and George Morgenstern's Pearl Harbor.
    - Detwiler, Don, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Fan Mail, 1949-1955 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Gole, Henry (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Heidenheimer, Arnold J. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - National Board of Consultants on the Humanities (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - O'Brien, Kenneth, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Psomas, Andreas, 1977-1979 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence: from Paul Gordon Lauren at U. of Montana; undated from Norman on Stanford memo paper, 17 May 1983 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence: from Wallace Notestein at Yale University regarding G. Craig's resignation, 9 May 1941 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Publishers
    - Holt, Henry [Dryden Press] (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Oxford University Press (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Publishers, including Oxford (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Lectures and teaching materials, 1940-1987; Series 2
  - Lecture Notes/Course Outlines
    - Colloquium Notes: "American Foreign Policy from FDR to JFK," Berlin, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
    - Lectures on Arms Control, Stanford [Arms Control and Disarmament: Hist 138a], 1970s (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Arms Control Course (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
    - Art, Politics and Society (Colloquium) [History 101e, 1971] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Austria to 1914 [History 239/339] (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Bismarck Seminar [History 427 & 328, 1961-1963] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Britain in 18th and 19th Centuries Lectures: Stanford in Britain, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Britain in 19th Century Lectures: Stanford in Britain, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Britain since 1914 Lectures: Stanford in Britain, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6-9)
    - Colloquium: British Conservatism (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - British History (Cliveden) [History 144B, 1971] (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - British History and Literature: Hauptseminar FU Berlin Sommersemester, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Development of a National Feeling in Germany to 1891: selected readings translated and edited by G.A. Craig (Source books in History 10) Yale University, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Diplomacy Seminar, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Diplomacy Seminar FU Berlin, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - #227: Grad Seminar - Diplomacy, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Diplomacy - Seminar Papers (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Diplomacy - Seminar Papers (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - History 135 [Diplomacy] (Box 3, Folder 6-11)
    - H135 Diplomatic Revolution Lectures (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Diplomatic Revolution Course [History 135], 1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Economic/Social History Europe, Princeton Harvard, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    - Europe 1815-70 (Grad) (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Core Colloquium [European Core Colloquium History 331D, 1980-81] (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - The First World War, History 228 (Box 4, Folder 6-9)
    - Germany in the 19th Century (147) (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Lecture Notes: Germany in the 19th Century History 128 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
    - Lecture Notes: Germany in the 19th Century History 128 (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
    - Lecture Notes: Germany in the 19th Century History 129 (Box 5, Folder 9-12)
    - Lecture Notes: Germany in the 19th Century History 129 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Germany in the 20th Century [History 129] (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - H129 Germany in the 20th Century Lectures 1914-1923 (Box 6, Folder 4-7)
    - H129 Germany in the 20th Century Lectures 1923-1933 (Box 6, Folder 8-11)
    - H129 Germany in the 20th Century Lectures 1933-1975 (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
    - German Seminar, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Colloquium: German Themes I [History 327B, 1976-1977] (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Colloquium: German Themes II [History 327A, 1978-1979] (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - [History 228: German Intellectuals and Politics 1770-1830, Autumn 1966] (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
    - German Question FU Colloquium [Free University of Berlin], 1976 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Germany since 1945, Stanford, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - The German Novel and Social Reality 1870-1945 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Grad Course 1985 [History of Foreign Relations, 1890-Present, Hist 331F] (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Hitler Colloquium [History 229A/329A, 1981] (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Humboldt Seminar (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Colloquium: Age of Imperialism (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - [Instructor's Orientation Course, 1944] (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Undergrad Colloquium: Magic Mountain, [Intellectual History of the 20th Century, History 101d], 1968 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Basic Seminar [International History, 100D] (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Invention and History: A Jape (Princeton -, 1950s) (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Lecture: Popish Plot, Princeton, 1950s (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Humanities Lectures Stanford, St. Paul [Humanities 201], 1960s (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - 1919 Seminar: Kohler (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Literatur und Politik in Deutschland 1900-1933 Berlin, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 1-5)
    - Lecture Notes: Literatur und Politik (Box 9, Folder 6-12)
    - History 1,2,3 [Modern Europe] (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - History II: Europe 1648-1848 Lectures [Modern Europe] (Box 10, Folder 2-5)
    - History III: Lectures 1815-1890 [Modern Europe] (Box 10, Folder 6-11)
    - History III: Lectures 1890-1914 [Modern Europe] (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    - History III: Lectures 1914-1970 [Modern Europe] (Box 11, Folder 3-6)
    - Seminar Papers History 228: Modern Germany, Fall 1965 (Box 11, Folder 7-9)
    - Undergrad Colloquium-Rationalism & Irrationalism (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Russia - Foreign Policy (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Colloq: Some Modern Historians [Hist 191, 1979] (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Seminar: World War II [1965-1966] [Second World War] (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Colloq: World War II [Second World War History 239A] (Box 11, Folder 14-15)
    - Structured Liberal Education, [1974] (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Seminar on Teaching Methods [Princeton, 1950s] (Box 12, Folder 2-4)
    - History 327 [The Reign of William II, History 328 Western Europe and Great Britain 1850 - 1890, and Topics in German History 1918-1933] (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Colloquia Winter [Including The Western Powers and the German Question 1919-39 and Social History of Modern France, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - [The Western Powers and the German Question 1919-39, taught at Free University in Berlin] (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Seminar Papers from History 228 "The Weimar Republic in the Light of Contemporary Literature," Vol. I-II, 1962
      - "George Grosz and the Face of Weimar Germany's Ruling Class," -Kenneth W. Rock (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - "Alfred Doblin's November 1918: A Novelistic Contribution to the History of the Weimar Republic," -William B. Cohen (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - "Toller as a Social Critic," -C.L. Warwick (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - "Bavarian Politics and Society as Seen Through the Eyes of Lion Feuchtwanger and his novel Erfoig," -Sybil Halprin (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - "The Defense of Upper Silesia in Fact and Fiction," -Warren E. Gade (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - "The Problem of Values in the Weimar Republic as Seen Through the Works of Erich Kaestner and Ernst Juenger," Diethelm Prowe (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - "Edwin Erich Dwinger's Attitude Toward War as Reflected in his Trilogy Die Deutsche Passion," -Romana Danysh (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - "Blunck, Beumelburg, and Wehner 1930: The Literary Harzburger Front," -James L. DeMarce (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - "The Farmer's Uprising of 1929 and Its Description in Novels by Fallada and Von Salomon," -Nicholas A. Zindler (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - "German Youth: 1919-1933 A Search for Authority," -Katherine Larson (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Seminar Papers from the course "Die Geschichte der Weimarer Republik im Spiegel ihrer Literatur," Berlin, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 11-16)
    - Seminar paper by Agatha Kunze; letters from Kunze and Manfred Bosch, (in German), 1989 (Box 13, Folder 17-18)
    - Lecture Notes and Seminar Papers from the course "Die Geschichte der Weimarer Republik im Spiegel ihrer Literatur," Berlin, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
    - Graduate Seminar: Wilhelm Von Humboldt: Leben und Work, Stanford, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 4-8)
    - Bibliography - First File [Miscellaneous Course Materials] (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Course Outlines, 1957-58 [1946-1958] (Box 14, Folder 10-11)
    - Course Outlines, 1970-1971 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - [Miscellaneous Lecture Notes and Grade book] (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - [Miscellaneous Course Lectures and Outlines] (Box 14, Folder 14-15)
  - Exams
    - Exams (Box 15, Folder 1-11)
  - Student Theses
    - "Deutschland Her Im Weltenmeer: The German Naval Intelligence Service in the United States 1900-18," Donald Abenheim, 1977 (Box 16a)
    - "Von Tirpitz's Legacy: The Panzerschiff 'A' and Strategic Continuity in the Weimar Republic," Donald Abenheim, 1978-9 (Box 16a)
    - "Ernst Junger The First Fifty Years," Deborah M. Africa, 1976 (Box 16b)
    - "The Lion in Flanders Awakens: the Flemish Movement from Caesar to Baudouin," Roy Coox, 1979 (Box 16b)
    - "The Development of the Canadian Expeditionary Force During the First World War 1914-1918," John D. Croll, 1978 (Box 16b)
    - Dissertation by Manfred Kleim from Humboldt University in Berlin, entitled "Genesis die Fuhrungshraffe der feudal-militaristischen Konterrevolution, 1848 in Preußen.", 1966 (Box 17, Folder 1-6)
  - Other Lectures and Speeches, 1936-1987
    - Konrad Adenauer Seminar, [at Stanford], 1987 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Augsburg Conference Lecture, (1979) (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Lectures in Berlin, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Class Day Speeches [at Stanford] (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Diplomatic Revolution of Our Times Lecture, Smith College, 1975 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Dulles Lecture, Berlin, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Executive Seminar (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Executive Seminar (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Executive Seminar, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - German Conference [Princeton, 1960] (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - German Conference [Princeton, 1960] (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Germany between East and West Lecture, Wilmington, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Historiography (Berlin Speech, 1975) (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - History as Instrument of Policy [Conference at The Wilson Center, 1978] (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Mansfield Lecture Materials, 1982 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Mansfield Lecture Materials, 1982 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Military Establishment and Society Lecture Univ. of N. Iowa, 1973 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Phi Beta Kappa (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Phi Beta Kappa Lectures, [1965] (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Phi Beta Kappa Lectures, 1972 (Box 19, Folder 6-8)
    - Roots of American Diplomatic Style, 1976 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - [Lecture: "Traditional Objectives and Policies of Smaller Nation States,", 1958] (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Lectures and Miscellaneous Papers on Teaching (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Lecture: Urban History, Toronto, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Utah Speech [Interview with Fritz Stern] (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - War College Lectures, 1950s - 70s (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
    - TV Paper: War of Future, 1956 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Germany since 1945 Lecture World Affairs Council, Dec-78 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - G.A. Craig: Speeches & Addresses incl. Princeton Valedictory Speech], [1936-1960 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - G.A. Craig: Speeches & Addresses, [1936-1960] (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Lectures (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Lectures (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Speeches and Addresses, [1940s & 50s] (Box 20, Folder 9-12)
    - Miscellaneous Lectures, [1950s & 60s] (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
    - Lectures #3 [Miscellaneous Lectures, 1950s & 1960s] (Box 21, Folder 3-5)
    - Occasional Speeches Talks, etc., 1960s (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches, 1960s-70s (Box 21, Folder 7-8)
    - Miscellaneous Speeches [including retirement speech], 1960s-70s (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Lectures, Miscellaneous, 1970s, '80s (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous Lectures etc. on campus (Box 21, Folder 11)
- University administration, Series 3
  - Stanford University
    - Academic Freedom (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Arms Control (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Arms Control (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Arms Control (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Arms Control (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Central European Project (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - CSFP [Committee on Foreign Study Programs] -, October 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - German Committee (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - German Study Center (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - History 1,2,3 [Outlines and correspondence with lecturers] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - International Relations Program (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Commission on International Studies (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Personal (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Travel (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Free University of Berlin
    - Berlin (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Berlin (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Berlin (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Berlin (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Berlin Deal (Personal Correspondence) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Berlin Deal (Personal Correspondence) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Berlin Deal (Personal Correspondence) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - FU Berlin Crisis [Notgemeinschaft] (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - FU Berlin Crisis [Notgemeinschaft] (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - FU Berlin Crisis [Notgemeinschaft] (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Notgemeinschaft (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Notgemeinschaft (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Notgemeinschaft (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Notgemeinschaft (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Notgemeinschaft (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Writings and publications, 1934-1975; Series 4
  - Notes and Papers from G. Craig's student days, 1934-1940
    - British History [including notes from Oxford and Yale, 1934, 1937 1940] (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - "A Short History of the German Social Democracy from Lassalie to the End of the World War," submitted to the History Department by Gordon Craig, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The Failure of the German Democracy" G. Craig's senior thesis at Princeton, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Diplomatic and Other Papers, Department of History, History 317, Princeton, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Lectures: England, Princeton [Lecture notes from G. Craig's first lecture course while completing Ph.D. at Princeton], 1939-40 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - [Craig's notes re: Bismarck and the American Fleet, date unknown] (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
    - Great Britain - Foreign Policy [date unknown] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Notebook from Oxford in, 1938 (Box 2)
    - "The Belgian Railways Question," Notebook from Oxford in, 1938 (Box 2)
    - "The Belgian Railways Question," Notebook from Oxford in, 1938 (Box 2)
    - "Bibliography," Notebook from student days (Box 2)
    - "The Luxemburg Crisis," Notebook from student days. (Box 2)
  - Publications by G. Craig
    - Reading Diplomatic Correspondence (paper) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Diplomatic Style (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - [The Founding Fathers and the European Balance of Power] (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Draft notes and clippings for Craig's book The Germans
      - Table of Contents, Stereotypes, Diversity, Burden of History (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Religion (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Women, Dying for the Fatherland, Professors and Students (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Money, Socialism (Bebel/Brandt), Bureaucrats, Der Deutsche Bauer, Germans and Jews, The Blue Flower (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Wanderers, Music, Engagement and Neutrality, Overcoming the Past: GFR (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Overcoming the Past: GDR, Language, Persons, Misc (Box 3, Folder 9)